<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!-- (as copied on 2015/07/12)                     -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->

<backmatter xml:id="backmatter" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Back Matter</title> <!-- mostly for HTML sectioning -->

    <appendix>
<title>Algebra Skills Refresher</title>
<section><title>Numbers and Operations</title>
<subsection xml:id="Order-of-Operations"><title>Order of Operations</title>

<p>Numerical calculations often involve more than one operation. So that everyone agrees on how such expressions should be evaluated, we follow the order of operations.</p>

<assemblage><title>Order of Operations</title>
<p>
    <ol label="*1*">
        <li><p>
            Simplify any expressions within grouping symbols (parentheses, brackets, square root bars, or fraction bars). Start with the innermost grouping symbols and work outward.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Evaluate all powers and roots.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Perform multiplications and divisions in order from left to right.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Perform additions and subtractions in order from left to right.
        </p></li>
    </ol>
</p>
</assemblage>
</subsection>




<subsection><title>Parentheses and Fraction Bars</title>
<p>
    We can use parentheses to override the multiplication-first rule. Compare the two expressions below.
    <md>
        <mrow>\amp\text{The sum of 4 times 6 and 10} \amp\amp 4 \cdot 6 + 10</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp\text{4 times the sum of 6 and 10} \amp\amp  4(6 + 10)</mrow>
    </md>
</p>
<p>
    In the first expression, we perform the multiplication <m>4\times 6</m> first, but in the second expression we perform the addition <m>6 + 10</m> first, because it is enclosed in parentheses.
</p>
<p>
    The location (or absence) of parentheses can drastically alter the meaning of an expression. In the following example, note how the location of the parentheses changes the value of the expression.
</p>

<example xml:id="example-parentheses">
    <p>
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}5-3\cdot 4^2 \amp = 5-3\cdot 16\\
                \amp = 5-48=-43
                \end{aligned}                
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}5-(3\cdot 4)^2 \amp = 5-12^2\\
                \amp= 5-144 = -139
                 \end{aligned}
           </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}(5-3\cdot 4)^2 \amp = (5-12)^2\\
                \amp = (-7)^2 = 49
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}(5-3)\cdot 4^2 \amp = 2\cdot 16\\
                \amp = 32
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
</example>

<warning>
    <p>
        In the expression <m>5 − 12^2</m>, which appears in <xref ref="example-parentheses" autoname="yes"/>, the exponent <m>2</m> applies only to <m>12</m>, not to <m>-12</m>. Thus, <m>5 − 12^2 \ne 5 + 144</m>.
    </p>
</warning>

<p>
    The order of operations mentions other grouping devices besides parentheses: fraction bars and square root bars. Notice how the placement of the fraction bar affects the expressions in the next example.
</p>

<example>
    <p>
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}
                \frac{1+2}{3\cdot 4} \amp = \frac{3}{12}\\
                \amp = \frac{1}{4}
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}
                1+\frac{2}{3\cdot 4} \amp = 1+ \frac{2}{12}\\
                \amp = 1+\frac{1}{6}=\frac{7}{6}
                \end{aligned}                
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}
                \frac{1+2}{3}\cdot 4 \amp = \frac{3}{3}\cdot 4\\
                \amp = 1\cdot 4=4
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}
                1+\frac{2}{3}\cdot 4 \amp = 1+ \frac{8}{3}\\
                \amp = \frac{3}{3}+\frac{8}{3}=\frac{11}{3}
                \end{aligned}                
            </m></p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
</example>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Radicals</title>
<p>
    You are already familiar with square roots. Every nonnegative number has two square roots, defined as follows:
    <me>s ~~\text{ is a square root of }~~ n ~~\text{ if }~~s^2 = n</me>
    There are several other kinds of roots, one of which is called the <term index="yes" >cube root</term>, denoted by <m>\sqrt[3]{n}</m>. We define the cube root as follows.
</p>
<assemblage><title>Cube Roots</title><index>cube root</index>
<p>
    <me>b ~~\text{ is a cube root of }~~~ n ~~~\text{ if }~~~ b ~\text{ cubed equals }~~n.</me>
    In symbols, we write
    <me>b=\sqrt[3]{n} ~~\text{ if } ~~ b^3=n</me>
</p></assemblage>

<p>
    Although we cannot take the square root of a <em>negative number</em>, we can take the <em>cube root</em> of <em>any</em> real number. For example,
    <me>\sqrt[3]{64}=4 ~~\text{ because }~~ 4^3=64</me>
    and
    <me>\sqrt[3]{-27}=-3 ~~\text{ because }~~ (-3)^3=-27</me>
</p>
<p>
    In the order of operations, simplifying radicals and powers comes after parentheses but before products and quotients.
</p>

<example>
    <p>
        Simplify each expression.
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><m>3\sqrt[3]{-8}</m></li>
            <li><m>2-\sqrt[3]{-125}</m></li>
            <li><m>\displaystyle{\frac{6-\sqrt[3]{-27}}{2}}</m></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
<solution>
    <p>
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><m>3\sqrt[3]{-8}=3(-2)=-6</m></li>
            <li><m>2-\sqrt[3]{-125}=2-(-5)=7</m></li>
            <li><m>\displaystyle{\frac{6-\sqrt[3]{-27}}{2}=\frac{6-(-3)}{2}=\frac{9}{2}}</m></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

</subsection>



<subsection><title>Scientific Notation</title>
<p>
    Scientists and engineers regularly encounter very large numbers such as
    <me>5,980,000,000,000,000,000,000,000</me>
    (the mass of the Earth in kilograms) and very small numbers such as
    <me>0.000 \,000 \,000 \,000 \,000 \,000 \,000 \,001 \,67</me>
    (the mass of a hydrogen atom in grams). These numbers can be written in a more compact and useful form by using powers of <m>10</m>.
</p>
<p>
    In our base <m>10</m> number system, multiplying a number by a positive power of <m>10</m> has the effect of moving the decimal place <m>k</m> places to the right, where <m>k</m> is the exponent in the power of <m>10</m>. For example,
    <me>3.529 \times 10^2 = 352.9 ~~~\text{ and }~~~ 25 \times 104 = 250,000</me>
    Multiplying by a power of <m>10</m> with a negative exponent moves the decimal place to the left. For example,
    <me>1728 \times 10^{−3} = 1.728 ~~~\text{ and }~~~ 4.6 \times 10^{−5} = 0.000046</me>
</p>
<p>
    Using this property, we can write any number as the product of a number between <m>1</m> and <m>10</m> (including <m>1</m>) and a power of <m>10</m>. For example, the mass of the Earth and the mass of a hydrogen atom can be expressed as
    <me>5.98 \times 1024 \text{ kilograms}\hphantom{blank} \text{ and }\hphantom{blank}1.67 \times 10^{−24} \text{ gram}</me>
    respectively. A number written in this form is said to be expressed in <term index="yes" >scientific notation</term>.
</p>

<assemblage><title>To Write a Number in Scientific Notation:</title>
<p>
    <ol label="*1*">
        <li><p>
            Locate the decimal point so that there is exactly one nonzero digit to its left.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Count the number of places you moved the decimal point: This determines the power of <m>10</m>.
            <ol label="*a*">
                <li><p>
                    If the original number is greater than <m>10</m>, the exponent is positive.
                </p></li>
                <li><p>
                    If the original number is less than <m>1</m>, the exponent is negative.
                </p></li>
            </ol>
        </p></li>
    </ol>
</p>
</assemblage>

<example>
    <p>
        Write each number in scientific notation.
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}
                478,000 \amp = 4.78000 \times 10^5\\
                \amp = 4.78 \times 10^5
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}
                0.00032 \amp= 00003.2 \times 10^{−4}\\
                \amp = 3.2 \times 10^{-4}
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
</example>

<example>
    <p>
        The average American eats <m>110</m> kilograms of meat per year. It takes about <m>16</m> kilograms of grain to produce <m>1</m> kilogram of meat, and advanced farming techniques can produce about <m>6000</m> kilograms of grain on each hectare of arable land. (The hectare is <m>10,000</m> square meters, or just under <m>2 1⁄2</m> acres.) Now, the total land area of the Earth is about <m>13</m> billion hectares, but only about <m>11\%</m> of that land is arable. Is it possible for each of the <m>5.5</m> billion people on Earth to eat as much meat as Americans do?
    </p>
<solution>
    <p>
        First we will compute the amount of meat necessary to feed every person on Earth <m>110</m> kilograms per year. There are <m>5.5 \times 10^9</m> people on Earth.
        <me>(5.5\times 10^9 \text{ people})\times (110 \text{ kg/person}) = 6.05\times 10^{11} \text{ kg of meat}</me>
        Next we will compute the amount of grain needed to produce that much meat.
        <me>
            (16 \text{ kg of grain/kg of meat})\times (6.05\times 10^{11} \text{ kg of meat}) = 9.68\times 10^{12} \text{ kg of grain}
        </me>
        Next we will see how many hectares of land are needed to produce that much grain.
        <me>
            (9.68\times 10^{12} \text{ kg of grain})\div(6000 \text{ kg/hectare}) = 1.613\times 10^9 \text{ hectares}
        </me>
        Finally, we will compute the amount of arable land available for grain production.
        <me>0.11\times (13\times 10^9 \text{ hectares}) = 1.43\times 10^9 \text{ hectares}</me>
        Thus, even if we use every hectare of arable land to produce grain for livestock, we will not have enough to provide every person on Earth with <m>110</m> kilograms of meat per year.
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

</subsection>


<!--


-->
</section>

<section xml:id="appendix-Linear-Equations-and-Inequalities"><title>Linear Equations and Inequalities</title>
<p>An <term>equation</term> is just a mathematical statement that two expressions are equal. Equations relating two variables are particularly useful. If we know the value of one of the variables, we can find the corresponding value of the other variable by solving the equation.</p>

<example>
    <p>
        The equation <m>w = 6h</m> gives Loren's wages, <m>w</m>, in terms of the number of hours she works, <m>h</m>. How many hours does Loren need to work next week if she wants to earn <m>\$225</m>?
    </p>
<solution>
    <p>
        We know that <m>w = 225</m>, and we would like to know the value of <m>h</m>. We substitute the value for <m>w</m> into our equation and then solve for <m>h</m>.
        <md>
            <mrow>w \amp= 6h\amp\amp \text{Substitute 225 for }w.</mrow>
            <mrow>\alert{225} \amp= 6h\amp\amp \text{Divide both sides by } 6.</mrow>
            <mrow>\frac{225}{\alert{6}}\amp = \frac{6h}{\alert{6}}\amp\amp \text{Simplify.}</mrow>
            <mrow>375.5\amp = h</mrow>
        </md>
        Loren must work <m>37.5</m> hours in order to earn <m>\$225</m>. In reality, Loren will probably have to work for <m>38</m> hours, because most employers do not pay for portions of an hour's work. Thus, Loren needs to work for <m>38</m> hours.
    </p>
</solution></example>

<p>
    To solve an equation we can generate simpler equations that have the same solutions. Equations that have identical solutions are called <term index="yes">equivalent equations</term>. For example,
    <me>3x − 5 = x + 3</me>
    and
    <me>2x = 8</me>
    are equivalent equations because the solution of each equation is <m>4</m>. Often we can find simpler equivalent equations by undoing in reverse order the operations performed on the variable.
</p>

<subsection><title>Solving Linear Equations</title>
<p>
    <term>Linear</term>, or first-degree, equations can be written so that every term is either a constant or a constant times the variable. The equations above are examples of linear equations. Recall the following rules for solving linear equations.
</p>

<assemblage><title>To Generate Equivalent Equations</title>
<p>
    <ol label="*1*">
        <li><p>
            We can add or subtract the <em>same</em> number on <em>both</em> sides of an equation.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            We can multiply or divide <m>both</m> sides of an equation by the <m>same</m> number (except zero).
        </p></li>
    </ol>
</p>
</assemblage>

<p>
    Applying either of these rules produces a new equation equivalent to the old one and thus preserves the solution.We use the rules to isolate the variable on one side of the equation.
</p>

<example><p>
    Solve the equation <m>3x − 5 = x + 3</m>.
</p>
<solution>
    <p>
        We first collect all the variable terms on one side of the equation, and the constant terms on the other side.
        <md>
            <mrow>
                3x − 5 \alert{{}− x} \amp = x + 3 \alert{{}− x}\amp\amp \text{Subtract }x \text{ from both sides.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                2x − 5 \amp = 3\amp\amp \text{Simplify.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                2x − 5 \alert{{}+ 5} \amp = 5 \alert{{}+ 5}\amp\amp \text{Add 5 to both sides.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                2x \amp = 8 \amp\amp\text{Simplify.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                \frac{2x}{\alert{2}}\amp =\frac{8}{\alert{2}}\amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by 2.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>x\amp = 4\amp\amp\text{Simplify.}</mrow>
        </md>
        The solution is <m>4</m>. (You can check the solution by substituting <m>4</m> into the original equation to show that a true statement results.)
    </p>
</solution></example>

<p>
    The following steps should enable you to solve any linear equation. Of course, you may not need all the steps for a particular equation.
</p>

<assemblage><title>To Solve a Linear Equation:</title>
<p>
    <ol label="*1*">
        <li><p>
            Simplify each side of the equation separately.
            <ol label="*a*">
                <li><p>
                    Apply the distributive law to remove parentheses.
                </p></li>
                <li><p>
                    Collect like terms.
                </p></li>
            </ol>
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            By adding or subtracting appropriate terms to both sides of the equation, get all the variable terms on one side and all the constant terms on the other.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Divide both sides of the equation by the coefficient of the variable.
        </p></li>
    </ol>
</p>
</assemblage>

<example>
    <p>
        Solve <m>3(2x − 5) − 4x = 2x − (6 − 3x)</m>.
    </p>
<solution>
    <p>
        We begin by simplifying each side of the equation.
        <md>
            <mrow>
                3(2x − 5) − 4x \amp = 2x − (6 − 3x) \amp\amp\text{Apply the distributive law.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                6x − 15 − 4x \amp= 2x − 6 + 3x \amp\amp\text{Combine like terms on each side.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                2x − 15 \amp= 5x − 6
            </mrow>
        </md>
        Next, we collect all the variable terms on the left side of the equation, and all the constant terms on the right side.
        <md>
            <mrow>
                2x − 15 − 5x + 15 \amp= 5x − 6 − 5x + 15 \amp\amp\text{Add }−5x + 15 \text{ to both sides.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                −3x \amp= 9
            </mrow>
        </md>
        Finally, we divide both sides of the equation by the coefficient of the variable.
        <md>
            <mrow>
                −3x \amp= 9 \amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by }−3.
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                x \amp =-3
            </mrow>
        </md>
        The solution is <m>−3</m>.
    </p>
</solution></example>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Formulas</title>
<p>
    A <term index="yes" >formula</term> is an equation that relates several variables. For example, the equation 
    <me>P = 2l + 2w</me>
    gives the perimeter of a rectangle in terms of its length and width.
</p>
<p>
    Suppose we have some wire fence to enclose an exercise area for rabbits, and we would like to see what dimensions are possible for different rectangles with that perimeter. In this case, it would be more useful to have a formula for the length of the rectangle in terms of its perimeter and its width. We can find such a formula by solving the perimeter formula for <m>l</m> in terms of <m>P</m> and <m>w</m>.
    <md>
        <mrow>2l + 2w \amp= P \amp\amp\text{Subtact }2 w \text{ from both sides.}</mrow>
        <mrow>2l \amp= P − 2w \amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by 2.}</mrow>
        <mrow>l \amp= \frac{P − 2w}{2}</mrow>
    </md>
        The result is a new formula that gives the length of a rectangle in terms of its perimeter and its width.
</p>

<example>
<p>
    The formula <m>5F = 9C + 160</m> relates the temperature in degrees Fahrenheit, <m>F</m>, to the temperature in degrees Celsius, <m>C</m>. Solve the formula for <m>C</m> in terms of <m>F</m>.
</p>
<solution>
    <p>
        We begin by isolating the term that contains <m>C</m>.
        <md>
            <mrow>
                5F \amp= 9C + 160 \amp\amp\text{Subtract 160 from both sides.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                5F − 160 \amp = 9C \amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by 9.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                \frac{5F − 160}{9} \amp =C
            </mrow>
        </md>
        We can also write the formula for <m>C</m> in terms of <m>F</m> as <m>C = \frac{5}{9}F − \frac{160}{9}</m>.
    </p>
</solution></example>

<example>
    <p>
        Solve <m>3x − 5y = 40</m> for <m>y</m> in terms of <m>x</m>.
    </p>
<solution>
    <p>
        We isolate <m>y</m> on one side of the equation.
        <md>
            <mrow>
                3x − 5y \amp = 40\amp\amp\text{Subtract }3x \text{ from both sides.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                −5y \amp = 40 − 3x\amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by }-5.
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                 \frac{−5y}{-5} \amp = \frac{40 − 3x}{-5}\amp\amp\text{Simplify both sides.}               
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                y \amp = −8 + \frac{3}{5}x
            </mrow>
        </md>
    </p>
</solution></example>

</subsection>



<subsection><title>Linear Inequalities</title>
<p>
    The symbol <m>\gt</m> is called an <term index="yes">inequality symbol</term>, and the statement <m>a\gt b</m> is called an <term index="yes" >inequality</term>. There are four inequality symbols:
    <md>
        <mrow>\amp\gt \amp\amp\text{is greater than}</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp\lt \amp\amp\text{is less than}</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp\ge \amp\amp\text{is greater than or equal to}</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp\le \amp\amp\text{is less than or equal to}</mrow>
    </md>
</p>
<p>
    Inequalities that include the symbols <m>\gt</m> or <m>\le</m> are called <term index="yes">strict inequalities</term>; those that include <m>\ge</m> or <m>\le</m> are called <term index="yes">nonstrict</term>.
</p>
<p>
    If we multiply or divide both sides of an inequality by a negative number, the direction of the inequality must be reversed. For example, if we multiply both sides of the inequality
    <me>2\lt 5</me>
    by <m>−3</m>, we get
    <md>
        <mrow>\alert{−3}(2) \amp\gt \alert{−3}(5)\amp\amp \text{Change inequality symbol from }\lt \text{ to }\gt.</mrow>
        <mrow>−6 \amp\gt −15.</mrow>
    </md>
    Because of this property, the rules for solving linear equations must be revised slightly for solving linear inequalities.
</p>

<assemblage><title>To Solve a Linear Inequality:</title>
<p>
    <ol label="*1*">
        <li><p>
            We may add or subtract the same number to both sides of an inequality without changing its solutions.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            We may multiply or divide both sides of an inequality by a <em>positive</em> number without changing its solutions.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            If we multiply or divide both sides of an inequality by a <em>negative</em> number, we must <em>reverse the direction of the inequality symbol</em>.
        </p></li>
    </ol>
</p>
</assemblage>

<example>
    <p>
        Solve the inequality <m>4 − 3x \ge −17</m>.
    </p>
<solution>
    <p>
        Use the rules above to isolate <m>x</m> on one side of the inequality.
        <md>
            <mrow>
                4 − 3x \amp\ge −17\amp\amp\text{Subtract 4 from both sides.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                −3x \amp\ge −21\amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by }−3.
            </mrow>
            <mrow>x \amp\le 7</mrow>
        </md>
        Notice that we reversed the direction of the inequality when we divided by <m>-3</m>. Any number less than or equal to <m>7</m> is a solution of the inequality.
    </p>
</solution></example>

<p>
    A <term index="yes" >compound inequality</term> involves two inequality symbols.
</p>

<example xml:id="example-compound-inequality">
    <p>
        Solve <m>4 \le 3x + 10 \le 16</m>.
    </p>
<solution>
    <p>
        We isolate <m>x</m> by performing the same operations on all three sides of the inequality.
        <md alignment="alignat">
            <mrow>
                4 \amp{}\le{} 3x\amp {}+{}\amp 10 \amp{}\le{} 16\hphantom{blank} \amp\text{Subtract }10.
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                −6 \amp{}\le{} \amp 3x\amp {}{}\amp {}\le{} 6\hphantom{blank} \amp\text{Divide by }3.
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                −2 \amp{}\le{} \amp x\amp {}{}\amp{}\le{} 2\hphantom{blank}\amp
            </mrow>
        </md>
        The solutions are all numbers between <m>-2</m> and <m>2</m>, inclusive.
    </p>
</solution></example>

</subsection>



<subsection><title>Interval Notation</title>
<p>
    The solutions of the inequality in <xref ref="example-compound-inequality" autoname="yes"/> form an interval. An <term index="yes" >interval</term> is a set that consists of all the real numbers between two numbers <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>.
</p>
<p>
    The set <m>−2 \le x \le 2</m> includes its endpoints <m>-2</m> and <m>2</m>, so we call it a <term index="yes" >closed interval</term>, and we denote it by <m>[−2, 2]</m> (see <xref ref="fig-numline-closed-vs-open" autoname="yes"/>a). The square brackets tell us that the endpoints are included in the interval. An interval that does not include its endpoints, such as <m>−2 \lt x \lt 2</m>, is called an <term index="yes" >open interval</term>, and we denote it with round brackets, <m>(−2, 2)</m> (see <xref ref="fig-numline-closed-vs-open" autoname="yes"/>b).
    <figure xml:id="fig-numline-closed-vs-open"><image source="images/fig-numline-closed-vs-open" alt="closed interval and open interva"/><caption>       
    </caption> </figure>
</p>

<warning>
    <p>
        Do not confuse the open interval <m>(−2, 2)</m> with the point <m>(−2, 2)</m>! The notation is the same, so you must decide from the context whether an interval or a point is being discussed.
    </p>
</warning>

<p>
    We can also discuss <term index="yes">infinite intervals</term>, such as <m>x\lt 3</m> and <m>x\ge -1</m>, shown in <xref ref="fig-numline-infinite-intervals" autoname="yes"/>. We denote the interval <m>x\lt 3</m> by <m>(−\infty, 3)</m>, and the interval <m>x\ge -1</m> by <m>[−1, \infty)</m>. The symbol <m>\infty</m>, for infinity, does not represent a specific real number; it indicates that the interval continues forever along the real line.
   <figure xml:id="fig-numline-infinite-intervals"><image source="images/fig-numline-infinite-intervals" alt="infinite intervals"/><caption></caption> </figure> 
</p>
<p>
    Finally, we can combine two or more intervals into a larger set. For example, the set consisting of <m>x\lt -1</m> or <m>x\gt 2</m>, shown in <xref ref="fig-numline-disjoint-infinite-intervals" autoname="yes"/>, is the <term index="yes">union</term> of two intervals and is denoted by <m>(−\infty,−2) \cup (2,\infty)</m>.
    <figure xml:id="fig-numline-disjoint-infinite-intervals"><image source="images/fig-numline-disjoint-infinite-intervals" alt="number line with two disjoint infinite intervals"/><caption></caption> </figure>
</p>
<p>
    Many solutions of inequalities are intervals or unions of intervals.
</p>

<example>
    <p>
        Write each of the solution sets with interval notation and graph the solution set on a number line.
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><p><m>3 \le x \lt 6</m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>x \ge −9</m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>x\le 1 ~~\text{ or }~~ x\gt 4</m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>−8 \lt x \le −5 ~~\text{ or }~~ −1 \le x \lt 3</m></p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
<solution>
    <p>
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><p>
                <m>[3, 6)</m>. This is called a <term index="yes">half-open</term> or <term index="yes">half-closed</term> interval. (See <xref ref="fig-half-open-interval" autoname="yes"/>.)
                <figure xml:id="fig-half-open-interval"><image source="images/fig-half-open-interval" alt="half-open interval"/><caption></caption> </figure>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                <m>[−9,\infty)</m>. We always use round brackets next to the symbol <m>\infty</m> because <m>\infty</m> is not a specific number and is not included in the set. (See <xref ref="fig-half-closed-infinite-interval" autoname="yes"/>.)
                <figure xml:id="fig-half-closed-infinite-interval"><image source="images/fig-half-closed-infinite-interval" alt="half-closed infinite interval"/><caption></caption> </figure>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                <m>(−\infty, 1] \cup (4, \infty)</m>. The word <em>or</em> describes the union of two sets. (See <xref ref="fig-disjoint-infinite-intervals" autoname="yes"/>.)
                <figure xml:id="fig-disjoint-infinite-intervals"><image source="images/fig-disjoint-infinite-intervals" alt="disjoint infinite intervals"/><caption></caption> </figure>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                <m>(−8,−5] \cup [−1, 3)</m>. (See <xref ref="fig-disjoint-finite-intervals" autoname="yes"/>.)
                <figure xml:id="fig-disjoint-finite-intervals"><image source="images/fig-disjoint-finite-intervals" alt="disjoint finite intervals"/><caption></caption> </figure>
            </p></li>
        </ol>
        
    </p>
</solution>
</example>


</subsection>

</section>
<!-- 


    -->


<section xml:id="appendix-Algebraic-Expressions-and-Problem-Solving"><title>Algebraic Expressions and Problem Solving</title>
<p>You are familiar with the use of letters, or <term>variables</term>, to stand for unknown numbers in equations or formulas. Variables are also used to represent numerical quantities that change over time or in different situations. For example, <m>p</m> might stand for the atmospheric pressure at different heights above the Earth's surface. Or <m>N</m> might represent the number of people infected with cholera <m>t</m> days after the start of an epidemic.</p>
<p>
    An <term index="yes">algebraic expression</term> is any meaningful combination of numbers, variables, and symbols of operation. Algebraic expressions are used to express relationships between variable quantities.
</p>

<example xml:id="example-Loren">
    <p>
        Loren makes <m>\$6</m> an hour working at the campus bookstore.
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><p>
                Choose a variable for the number of hours Loren works per week.
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                Write an algebraic expression for the amount of Loren's weekly earnings.
            </p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
<solution>
    <p>
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><p>
                Let <m>h</m> stand for the number of hours Loren works per week.
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                The amount Loren earns is given by
                <me>6\times (\text{number of hours Loren worked})</me>
                or <m>6\cdot h</m>. Loren's weekly earnings can be expressed as <m>6h</m>.
            </p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
</solution></example>

<p>
    The algebraic expression <m>6h</m> represents the amount of money Loren earns <em>in terms of</em> the number of hours she works. If we substitute a specific value for the variable in an expression, we find a numerical value for the expression. This is called <term index="yes">evaluating</term> the expression.
</p>

<example>
    <p>
        If Loren from <xref ref="example-Loren" autoname="yes"/> works for <m>16</m> hours in the bookstore this week, how much will she earn?
    </p>
<solution>
    <p>
        Evaluate the expression <m>6h</m> for <m>h=\alert{16}</m>.
        <me>
            6h = 6(\alert{16}) = 96
        </me>
        Loren will make <m>\$96</m>.
    </p>
</solution></example>

<example xml:id="example-April">
    <p>
        April sells environmentally friendly cleaning products. Her income consists of <m>\$200</m> per week plus a commission of <m>9\%</m> of her sales.
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><p>
                Choose variables to represent the unknown quantities and write an algebraic expression for April's weekly income in terms of her sales.
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                Find April's income for a week in which she sells <m>\$350</m> worth of cleaning products.
            </p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
<solution>
    <p>
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><p>
                Let <m>I</m> represent April's total income for the week, and let <m>S</m> represent the total amount of her sales. We translate the information from the problem into mathematical language as follows:
                <md>
                    <mrow>
                       \text{Her income consists of }\$200 . . .\text{ plus }. . . 9\% \text{ of her sales} 
                    </mrow>
                    <mrow>
                        I \hphantom{consists of}= \hphantom{of}200 \hphantom{plus+}+ \hphantom{....}0.09 \hphantom{of her}S
                    </mrow>
                </md>
                Thus, <m>I = 200 + 0.09S</m>.
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                We want to evaluate our expression from part (a) with <m>S = 350</m>. We substitute <m>\alert{350}</m> for <m>S</m> to find
                <me>I = 200 + 0.09(\alert{350})</me>
                Following the order of operations, we perform the multiplication before the addition. Thus, we begin by computing <m>0.09(350)</m>.
                <md>
                    <mrow>
                        I \amp = 200 + 0.09(350)\amp\amp\text{Multiply }0.09 (350) \text{ first.}
                    </mrow>
                    <mrow>\amp = 200 + 31.5</mrow>
                    <mrow>\amp = 231.50</mrow>
                </md>
                April's income for the week is <m>\$231.50</m>.
            </p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
</solution></example>

<remark><title><image source="images/icon-GC.jpg" alt="Graphing Calculator" width="8%"  />Calculator Tip</title>
<p>
    On a scientific or a graphing calculator, we can enter the expression from <xref ref="example-April" autoname="yes"/> just as it is written:
    <me>200 + 0.09 ~ \boxed{\times}~ 350 ~\boxed{\text{ENTER}}</me>
    The calculator will perform the operations in the correct order—multiplication first.
</p></remark>

<example xml:id="example-parcel">
    <p>
        Economy Parcel Service charges <m>\$2.80</m> per pound to deliver a package from Pasadena to Cedar Rapids. Andrew wants to mail a painting that weighs <m>8.3</m> pounds, plus whatever packing material he uses.
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><p>
                Choose variables to represent the unknown quantities and write an expression for the cost of shipping Andrew's painting.
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                Find the shipping cost if Andrew uses <m>2.9</m> pounds of packing material.
            </p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
<solution>
    <p>
        <ol label="*a*">
            <li><p>
                Let <m>C</m> stand for the shipping cost and let <m>w</m> stand for the weight of the packing material. Andrew must find the total weight of his package first, then multiply by the shipping charge. The total weight of the package is <m>8.3 + w</m> pounds. We use parentheses around this expression to show that it should be computed first, and the sum should be multiplied by the shipping charge of <m>\$2.80</m> per pound. Thus,
                <me>C = 2.80(8.3 + w)</me>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                Evaluate the formula from part (a) with <m>w = \alert{2.9}</m>.
                <md>
                    <mrow>
                        C \amp = 2.80(8.3 + \alert{2.9})\amp\amp\text{Add inside parentheses.}
                    </mrow>
                    <mrow>
                        \amp = 2.80(11.2)\amp\amp\text{Multiply.}
                    </mrow>
                    <mrow>
                        \amp = 31.36
                    </mrow>
                </md>
                The cost of shipping the painting is <m>\$31.36</m>.
            </p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
</solution></example>

<remark><title><image source="images/icon-GC.jpg" alt="Graphing Calculator" width="8%"  />Calculator Tip</title>
<p>
    On a calculator, we enter the expression for <m>C</m> in the order it appears, including the parentheses. (Experiment to see whether your calculator requires you to enter the <c>×</c> symbol after 2.80.) The keying sequence
    <me>2.80 \times ( 8.3 + 2.9 ) \boxed{\text{ENTER}}</me>
    gives the correct result, <m>31.36</m>.
</p>
</remark>

<warning>
    <p>
        If we omit the parentheses, the calculator will perform the multiplication before the addition. Thus, the keying sequence
        <me>2.80 \times 8.3 + 2.9</me>
        gives an incorrect result for <xref ref="example-parcel" autoname="yes"/>. (The sequence
        <me>8.3 + 2.9 \times 2.80</me>
        does not work either!)
    </p>
</warning>

<subsection><title>Problem Solving</title>
<p>
    Problem solving often involves translating a real-life problem into a computer programming language, or, in our case, into algebraic expressions. We can then use algebra to solve the mathematical problem and interpret the solution in the context of the original problem. Here are some guidelines for problem solving with algebraic equations.
</p>

<assemblage><title>Guidelines for Problem Solving</title>
<p>
    <dl>
        <li><title>Step 1:</title><p>
            Identify the unknown quantity and assign a variable to represent it.
        </p></li>
        <li><title>Step 2:</title><p>
            Find some quantity that can be expressed in two different ways and write an equation.
        </p></li>
        <li><title>Step 3:</title><p>
            Solve the equation.
        </p></li>
        <li><title>Step 4:</title><p>
            Interpret your solution to answer the question in the problem.
        </p></li>
    </dl>
</p>

</assemblage>


</subsection>

</section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Graphs-and-Equations"><title>Graphs and Equations</title>
        <p>Graphs are useful tools for studying mathematical relationships. A graph provides an overview of a quantity of data, and it helps us identify trends or unexpected occurrences. Interpreting the graph can help us answer questions about the data.</p>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Linear-Systems-in-Two-Variables"><title>Linear Systems in Two Variables</title><index>linear system</index>
        <p>A <m>2\times 2</m> <term>system</term> of equations is a set of <m>2</m> equations in the same <m>2</m> variables. A <term index="yes">solution</term> of a <m>2\times 2</m> system is an ordered pair that makes each equation in the system true. In this section, we review two algebraic methods for solving <m>2\times 2</m> linear systems: substitution and elimination.</p>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Laws-of-Exponents"><title>Laws of Exponents</title><index>laws of exponents</index>
        <p>In this section, we review the rules for performing operations on powers.</p>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Polynomials-and-Factoring"><title>Polynomials and Factoring</title>
        <p>In <xref ref="appendix-Laws-of-Exponents" autoname="yes"/>, we used the first law of exponents to multiply two or more monomials. In this section, we review techniques for multiplying and factoring polynomials of several terms.</p>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Factoring-Quadratic-Trinomials"><title>Factoring Quadratic Trinomials</title>
        <p>Consider the trinomial
            <me>
                x^2 + 10x + 16
            </me>
        </p>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Working-with-Algebraic-Fractions"><title>Working with Algebraic Fractions</title>
        <p>
            A quotient of two polynomials is called a <term index="yes">rational expression</term> or an <term index="yes">algebraic fraction</term>. Operations on algebraic fractions follow the same rules as operations on common fractions.
        </p>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Working-with-Radicals"><title>Working with Radicals</title>
        <p>In some situations, radical notation is more convenient to use than exponents. In these cases, we usually simplify radical expressions algebraically as much as possible before using a calculator to obtain decimal approximations.</p>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Facts-from-Geometry"><title>Facts from Geometry</title>
        <p>
            In this section, we review some information you will need from geometry. You are already familiar with the formulas for the area and perimeter of common geometric figures; you can find these formulas in the reference section at the front of the book.
        </p>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-The-Real-Number-System"><title>The Real Number System</title>
        <subsection><title>Subsets of the Real Numbers</title>
        <p>
            The numbers associated with points on a number line are called the <term index="yes">real numbers</term>. The set of real numbers is denoted by <m>\mathbb{R}</m>. You are already familiar with several types, or subsets, of real numbers:
        </p>
        </subsection>
        </section>

    </appendix>



    <appendix>
        <title>Using a Graphing Calculator</title>
        <introduction><p>This appendix provides instructions for TI-84 or TI-83 calculators from Texas Instruments, but most other calculators work similarly.We describe only the basic operations and features of the graphing calculator used in your textbook.</p></introduction>
        <section xml:id="appendix-Getting-Started"><title>Getting Started</title>
        <subsection><title>On and Off</title>
        <p>
            Press <c>ON</c> to turn <em>on</em> the calculator (see Figure B.1a). You will see a cursor blinking in the upper left corner of the Home screen. Press <c>2nd</c><c>ON</c> to turn <em>off</em> the calculator.
        </p>

        </subsection>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Entering-Expressions"><title>Entering Expressions</title>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Editing-Expressions"><title>Editing Expressions</title>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Graphing-an-Equation"><title>Graphing an Equation</title>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Making-a-Table"><title>Making a Table</title>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Regression"><title>Regression</title>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="appendix-Function-Notation-and-Transformation-of-Graphs"><title>Function Notation and Transformation of Graphs</title>

        </section>

        </appendix>

    <appendix><title>Glossary</title>
    </appendix>

    <appendix>
        <title>Answers to selected exercises</title>
    </appendix>

<!--    <xi:include href="./gfdl-mathbook.xml" /> -->          <!-- GFDL License text -->

    <!-- Index follows appendices, preceded only colophon -->
    <index-part>

        <index-list />
    </index-part>

    <colophon>
        <p>This book was authored in MathBook XML.</p>
    </colophon>

</backmatter>