<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="Joint-Variation"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Joint Variation</title>


<subsection><title>Functions of Two or More Variables</title>
<p>
    So far, we have studied functions that relate values of an output variable to values of a single input variable. But it is not uncommon for an output variable to depend on two or more inputs. Many familiar formulas describe functions of several variables. For example, the perimeter of a rectangle depends on its length and width. The volume of a cylinder depends on its radius and height. The distance you travel depends on your speed and the time you spent traveling. Each of these formulas can be written with function notation.
    \begin{align*}
    \amp P = f (l,w) = 2l + 2w \amp\amp \text{Perimeter is a function of length and width.}\\
    \amp V = f (r, h) = πr 2h \amp\amp \text{Volume is a function of radius and height.}\\
    \amp d = f (r, t) = rt \amp\amp \text{Distance is a function of rate and time.}
    \end{align*}
</p>

<example xml:id="example-rental-car">
<p>
    The cost, <m>C</m>, of driving a rental car is given by the function
    <me>C = f (t, g) = 29.95t + 2.80g</me>
    where <m>t</m> is the number of days you rent the car and <m>g</m> is the number of gallons of gas you buy.
</p>
<ol label="*a*">
    <li>Evaluate <m>f (3,10)</m> and explain what it means.</li>
    <li>You have <dollar/>100 to rent a car for <m>2</m> days. How much gas can you buy?</li>
</ol>
<solution>
    <ol label="*a*">
        <li>We substitute <m>3</m> for <m>t</m> and <m>10</m> for <m>g</m> to find
        <me>f (3, 10) = 29.95(3) + 2.80(10) = 117.85</me>
        It will cost <dollar/><m>117.85</m> to rent a car for <m>3</m> days and buy <m>10</m> gallons of gas.</li>
        <li>We would like to find the value of <m>g</m> when <m>t = 2</m> and <m>C = 100</m>. That is, we want to solve the equation
        \begin{align*}
        100 \amp = f (2, g) = 29.95(2) + 2.80g \\
        100 \amp = 59.90 + 2.80g \\
        g \amp = 14.32
        \end{align*}
        You can buy <m>14.32</m> gallons of gas.
    </li>
</ol>
</solution>
</example>

<exercise xml:id="exercise-water-stream"><statement>
<p>
    The maximum height that the water stream from a fire hose can reach depends on the water pressure and the diameter of the nozzle, and is given by the function
    <me>H = f (P, n) = 26 + \frac{5}{8}P + 5n</me>
    where <m>P</m> is the nozzle pressure in psi, and <m>n</m> is measured in <m>18</m>-inch increments over the standard nozzle diameter of <m>\frac{3}{4}</m> inch.
    <ol label="*a*">
        <li>Evaluate <m>f (40, 2)</m> and explain what it means.</li>
        <li>What nozzle pressure is needed to reach a height of <m>91</m> feet with a <m>1\frac{1}{8}</m>-inch nozzle?</li>
    </ol>
</p>
</statement></exercise>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Tables of Values</title>
<p>
    Just as for functions of a single variable, we can use tables to describe functions of two variables, <m>z = f (x, y)</m>. The row and column headings show the values of the two input variables, and the table entries show the values of the output variable.
</p>


</subsection>


</section> 
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->