<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="Logarithms"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Logarithms</title>

<p>
	In this section, we introduce a new mathematical tool called a <em>logarithm</em>, which will help us solve exponential equations.
</p>
<p>
	Suppose that a colony of bacteria doubles in size every day. If the colony starts with <m>50</m> bacteria, how long will it be before there are <m>800</m> bacteria? We answered questions of this type in <xref ref="exponential-functions" autoname="yes"/> by writing and solving an exponential equation. The function
	<me>P(t) = 50 \cdot 2^t</me>
	gives the number of bacteria present on day <m>t</m>, so we must solve the equation
	<me>800 = 50 \cdot 2^t</me>
	Dividing both sides by 50 yields
	<me>16 = 2^t</me>
	The solution of this equation is the answer to the following question: To what power must we raise <m>2</m> in order to get <m>16</m>?
</p>
<p>
	The value of <m>t</m> that solves the equation is called the base <m>2</m> <term index="yes">logarithm</term> of <m>16</m>. Since <m>2^4 = 16</m>, the base <m>2</m> logarithm of <m>16</m> is <m>4</m>. We write this as
	<me>\log_{2}16 = 4</me>
	In other words, we solve an exponential equation by computing a logarithm. You can check that <m>t = \alert{4}</m>
	solves the problem stated above:
	<me>P(\alert{4}) = 50 \cdot 2^\alert{4}= 800</me>
</p>
<p>
	Thus, the unknown exponent is called a logarithm. In general, for positive values of <m>b</m> and <m>x</m>, we make the following definition.
</p>
<definition><title>Logarithm</title>
<statement>
	The <term index="yes">base <m>b</m> logarithm of <m>x</m></term>, written <m>\log_{b} x</m>, is the exponent to which <m>b</m> must be raised in order to yield <m>x</m>.
</statement></definition>
<p>
	It will help to keep in mind that a logarithm is just an exponent. Some logarithms, like some square roots, are easy to evaluate, while others require a calculator. We will start with the easy ones.
<p>
	
</p>

<subsection><title></title>
<p>
</p>





</subsection>


</section> 
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->