<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="Exponential-Growth-and-Decay"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Exponential Growth and Decay</title>


<subsection><title>Exponential Growth</title>
<p>
    The functions in Investigation 7 describe exponential growth. During each time interval of a fixed length, the population is multiplied by a certain constant amount. In Part A, the bacteria population grows by a factor of <m>3</m> every day.
</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-table-bacteria-population"><image source="images/fig-table-bacteria-population" alt="table of bacteria population" width="80%"/></figure>
<p>
    For this reason, we say that <m>3</m> is the <term index="yes">growth factor</term> for the function. Functions that describe exponential growth can be expressed in a standard form.
</p>
<definition><title>Exponential Growth</title><statement>
<p></p><p>
    The function
    <me>P(t) = P_0 b^t</me>
    models exponential growth.
</p>
<p>
    <m>P_0 = P(0)</m> is the <term index="yes">initial value</term> of <m>P</m>;
</p>
<p>
    <m>b</m> is the <term index="yes">growth factor</term>.
</p>
</statement></definition>

<p>
    For the bacteria population, we have
    <me>P(t) = 100 \cdot 3^t</me>
    so <m>P_0 = 100</m> and <m>b = 3</m>.
</p>

<example xml:id="example-bacteria">
<p>
    A colony of bacteria starts with <m>300</m> organisms and doubles every week.
    <ol label="*a*">
        <li>Write a formula for the population of the bacteria colony after <m>t</m> weeks.</li>
        <li>How many bacteria will there be after <m>8</m> weeks? After <m>5</m> days?</li>
    </ol>
</p>
<solution>
    <ol label="*a*">
        <li>The initial value of the population was <m>P_0 = 300</m>, and its weekly growth factor is <m>b = 2</m>. Thus, a formula for the population after <m>t</m> weeks is
        <me>P(t) = 300 \cdot 2^t</me>
        </li>
        <li>After <m>8</m> weeks, the population will be
        <me>P(8) = 300 \cdot 2^8 = 76,800 \text{ bacteria}</me>
        Because <m>5</m> days is <m>\frac{5}{7}</m> of a week, after <m>5</m> days the population will be
        <me>P\left(\frac{5}{7}\right)= 300 \cdot 2^{5/7} = 492.2</me>
        We cannot have a fraction of a bacterium, so we round to the nearest whole number, <m>492</m>.</li>
    </ol>
</solution>
</example>

<paragraphs><title>Caution</title>
<p>
    In <xref ref="example-bacteria" autoname="yes"/>a, note that
    <me>300 \cdot 2^8 \ne 600^8</me>
    According to the order of operations, we compute the power <m>2^8</m> first, then multiply by <m>300</m>.
</p>
</paragraphs>

<exercise xml:id="exercise-fruit-flies"><statement>
<p>
    A population of <m>24</m> fruit flies triples every month. 
    <ol label="*a*">
        <li>
            Write a formula for the population of the bacteria colony after <m>t</m> weeks.
        </li>
        <li>
            How many fruit flies will there be after <m>6</m> months? After <m>3</m> weeks? (Assume that a month equals <m>4</m> weeks.)
        </li>
    </ol>
</p>
</statement></exercise>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Growth Factors</title>
<p>
    In Part B of Investigation 7, the rabbit population grew by a factor of <m>2</m> every <m>3</m> months.
</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-table-rabbit-population"><image source="images/fig-table-rabbit-population" alt="table of rabbit population" width="80%"/></figure>
<p>
    To write the growth formula for this population, we divide the value of <m>t</m> by <m>3</m> to find the number of doubling periods.
    <me>P(t) = 60 \cdot 2^{t/3}</me>
    To see the growth factor for the function, we use the third law of exponents to write <m>2^{t/3}</m> in another form. Recall that to raise a power to a power, we multiply exponents, so
    <me>\left(2^{1/3}\right)^t = 2^{t (1/3)} = 2^{t/3}</me>
    The growth law for the rabbit population is thus
    <me>P(t) = 60 \cdot \left(2^{1/3}\right)^t</me>
    The initial value of the function is <m>P_0 = 60</m>, and the growth factor is <m>b = 2^{1/3}</m>, or approximately <m>1.26</m>. The rabbit population grows by a factor of about <m>1.26</m> every month.
</p>
<p>
    If the units are the same, a population with a larger growth factor grows faster than one with a smaller growth factor.
</p>   

<example xml:id="example-compare-growth-factors">
<p>
    A lab technician compares the growth of <m>2</m> species of bacteria. She starts <m>2</m> colonies of <m>50</m> bacteria each. Species A doubles in population every <m>2</m> days, and species B triples every <m>3</m> days. Find the growth factor for each species.
</p>
<solution><p>
    A function describing the growth of species A is
    <me>P(t) = 50 \cdot 2^{t/2} = 50 \cdot \left(\alert{2^{1/2}}\right)^t</me>
    so the growth factor for species A is <m>\alert{2^{1/2}}</m>, or approximately <m>1.41</m>. For species B,
    <me>P(t) = 50 \cdot 3^{t/3} = 50 \cdot \left(\alert{3^{1/3}}\right)^t</me>
     so the growth factor for species B is <m>\alert{3^{1/3}}</m>, or approximately <m>1.44</m>. Species B grows faster than species A.
</p></solution>
</example>

<exercise xml:id="exerise-internet-providers"><statement><p>
    In 1999, analysts expected the number of Internet service providers to double in five years.
    <ol label="*a*">
        <li>What was the annual growth factor for the number of Internet service providers?</li>
        <li>If there were <m>5078</m> Internet service providers in April 1999, estimate the number of providers in April 2000 and in April 2001.</li>
        <li>Write a formula for <m>I (t)</m>, the number of Internet service providers <m>t</m> years after 1999.
        <p>Source: LA Times, Sept. 6, 1999</p></li>
    </ol>
</p></statement></exercise>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Percent Increase</title>
<p>
    Exponential growth occurs in other circumstances, too. For example, if the interest on a savings account is compounded annually, the amount of money in the account grows exponentially.
</p>
<p>
    Consider a principal of <dollar/>100 invested at 5<percent/> interest compounded annually. At the end of <m>1</m> year, the amount is
    \begin{align*}
    \text{Amount} \amp = \text{Principal} + \text{Interest} \\
    A \amp = P + Pr\\
    \amp = 100 + 100(0.05) = 105
    \end{align*}
    It will be more useful to write the formula for the amount after <m>1</m> year in factored form.
    \begin{align*}
    A \amp = P + Pr \amp\amp \text{Factor out P.} \\
    \amp = P(1 + r)
    \end{align*}
    With this version of the formula, the calculation for the amount at the end of <m>1</m> year looks like this:
    \begin{align*}
    A \amp = P(1 + r ) \\
    \amp = 100(1 + 0.05) \\
    \amp = 100(1.05) = \alert{105}
    \end{align*}
</p>
<p>
    The amount, <dollar/>105, becomes the new principal for the second year. To find the amount at the end of the second year, we apply the formula again, with <m>P = 105</m>.
    \begin{align*}
    A \amp = P(1 + r ) \\
    \amp = 105(1 + 0.05) \\
    \amp = \alert{105}(1.05) = 110.25
    \end{align*}
    Observe that to find the amount at the end of each year, we multiply the principal by a factor of <m>1 + r = 1.05</m>. Thus, we can express the amount at the end of the second year as
    \begin{align*}
    A \amp = [100(1.05)](1.05) \\
    \amp = 100(1.05)^2
    \end{align*}
    and at the end of the third year as
    \begin{align*}
    A \amp = \left[100(1.05)^2\right](1.05) \\
    \amp = 100(1.05)^3
    \end{align*}
</p>
<sidebyside><paragraphs width="70%">
<p>
    At the end of each year, we multiply the old balance by another factor of <m>1.05</m> to get the new amount. We organize our results into <xref ref="table-percent-increase" autoname="yes"/>, where <m>A(t)</m> represents the amount of money in the account after <m>t</m> years. For this example, a formula for the amount after <m>t</m> years is
    <me>A(t) = 100(1.05)^t</me>
</p></paragraphs>
<table xml:id="table-percent-increase" valign="top"><caption></caption><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>t</m></cell>
        <cell><m>P(1 + r)^t</m></cell>
        <cell><m>A(t)</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><m>0</m></cell>
        <cell><m>100</m></cell>
        <cell><m>100</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><m>1</m></cell>
        <cell><m>100(1.05)</m></cell>
        <cell><m>105</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><m>2</m></cell>
        <cell><m>100(1.05)^2</m></cell>
        <cell><m>110.25</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><m>3</m></cell>
        <cell><m>100(1.05)^3</m></cell>
        <cell><m>115.76</m></cell>
    </row>
</tabular></table>
</sidebyside>

<p>
    In general, for an initial investment of <m>P</m> dollars at an interest rate <m>r</m> compounded annually, we have the following formula for the amount accumulated after <m>t</m> years.
</p>

</subsection>


</section> 
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->