<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="Bibliography"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Bibliography</title>

<p>
	Ahrens, C. Donald. Essentials of Meteorology. Belmont, CA: Wadsworth,
1998.
Alexander, R. M. The Human Machine. Natural History Museum
Publications, 1992.
Altenburg, Edgar. Genetics. New York: Holt Rinehart and
Winston, 1956.
Atkins, P. W. and Beran, J. A. General Chemistry. Scientific American
Books, 1989.
Baddeley, Alan D. Essentials of Human Memory. Psychology Press Ltd.,
1999.
Belovsky, G. E. “Diet Optimization in a Generalist Herbivore: The
Moose.” Theoretical Population Biology, 14 (1978), 105–134.
Belovsky, G. E. “Generalist Herbivore Foraging and Its Role in Competitive
Interactions.” American Zoologist, 26 (1986), 51–69.
Bender, Edward. An Introduction to Mathematical Modeling. Mineola, NY:
Dover Publications, 1978.
Berg, Richard and Stork, David. The Physics of Sound. Englewood Cliffs,
NJ: Prentice-Hall, 1982.
Boleman, Jay. Physics, a Window on Our World. Englewood Cliffs,
NJ: Prentice Hall, 1982.
Bolton, William. Patterns in Physics. McGraw Hill, 1974.
Brandt, John C. and Maran, Stephen P. New Horizons in Astronomy. San
Francisco: W. H. Freeman, 1972.
Briggs, David and Courtney, Frank. Agriculture and Environment.
Singapore: Longman Scientific and Technical, 1985.
Burton, R. F. Biology by Numbers. Cambridge: Cambridge University
Press, 1998.
Carr, Bernard, and Giddings. Steven. “Quantum Black Holes.” Scientific
American, May 2005.
Chapman J. L. and Reiss M. J. Ecology: Principles and Applications.
Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1992.
Davis, Kimmet, and Autry. Physical Education: Theory and Practice.
Macmillan Education Australia PTY Ltd., 1986.
Deffeyes, Kenneth. Hubbert’s Peak. Princeton: Princeton University
Press, 2001.
The Earth and Its Place in the Universe. Open University, Milton Keynes,
1998.
Fowler, Murray and Miller, Eric. Zoo and Wild Animal Medicine.
Saunders, 1999.
Gillner, Thomas C. Modern Ship Design. U.S. Naval Institute
Press, 1972.
The Guiness Book of Records, 1998. Guinness Publishing Ltd., 1997.
Hayward, Geoff. Applied Ecology. Thomas Nelson and Sons, Ltd., 1992.
Holme, David J., and Peck, Hazel. Analytical Biochemistry. Longman
Scientific and Technical, 1993.
Hunt, J. A. and Sykes, A. Chemistry. Longman Group Ltd., 1984.
Hutson, A. H. The Pocket Guide to Mammals of Britain and Europe.
Dragon’s World Ltd., 1995.
Ingham, Neil. Astrophysics. International Thomson Publishing, 1997.
Karttunen, H. et al. Fundamental Astronomy. Springer-Verlag, 1987.
Krebs J. R. and Davies N. B. An Introduction to Behavioural Ecology.
Oxford: Blackwell Scientific Publications, 1993.
Leopold, Luna B., Wolman, M. Gordon, and Miller, John P. Fluvial
Processes in Geomorphology, New York: Dover Publications, Inc.,
1992.
Mannering, Fred, and Kilareski, Walter. Principles of Highway Engineering
and Traffic Analysis. New York: John Wiley and Sons, Inc., 1998.
Meadows, Donella, Randers, Jorgen, and Meadows, Dennis. Limits to
Growth, the 30-Year Update. White River Junction, VT: Chelsea Green
Publishing Co., 2004.
Mee, Frederick. Sound. Heinemann Educational Books, 1967.
Oglesby, Clarkson and Hicks, R. Gary. Highway Engineering. New York:
John Wiley and Sons, Inc., 1982.
Oliver, C. P. “The Effect of Varying the Duration of X-Ray Treatment
upon the Frequency of Mutation,” Science, 71 (1930), 44–46.
Perrins, C. M. British Tits. Collins, London, 1979.
Perrins, C. M. and Moss, D. “Reproductive Rates in the Great Tit.”
Journal of Animal Ecology, 44 (1975), 695–706.
Plummer, David. Biochemistry, the Chemistry of Life. London:
McGraw-Hill Book Co., 1989.
Pope, Jean A. Medical Physics. Heinemann Educational, 1989.
P. E. di Prampero et al. Journal of Applied Physiology, 37 (1974), 1–5.
Pratt, Paul W. Principles and Practices of Veterinary Technology. Mosby,
1998.
Pugh, L. G. C. E. “Relation of Oxygen Intake and Speed in Competition
Cycling and Comparative Observations on the Bicycle Ergometer.”
Journal of Physiology, 241 (1974), 795–808
Scarf, Philip. “An Empirical Basis for Naismith’s Rule.” Mathematics
Today, vol. 34 no. 5 (1998), 149–151
Schad, Jerry. Afoot and Afield in Los Angeles County. Berkeley:
Wilderness Press, 1991.
Schmidt-Nielsen, Knut. How Animals Work. Cambridge: Cambridge
University Press, 1972.
Schmidt-Nielsen, Knut. Scaling: Why Is Animal Size so Important?
Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1984.
Sears, Francis. Mechanics, Heat, and Sound.
Sternberg, Robert J. In Search of the Human Mind. Harcourt Brace
College Publishing, 1995.
Storch, Hammon, and Bunch. Ship Production. Cornell Maritime Press,
1988.
Strickberger, Monroe W. Genetics. Macmillan, 1976.
Underwood, Benton J. “Forgetting.” Scientific American, vol. 210, no. 3,
91–99.
Weisberg, Joseph and Parish, Howard. Introductory Oceanography.
McGraw-Hill, 1974.
Wilkinson, G. S. “Reciprocal Food Sharing in the Vampire Bat. Nature,
308 (1984), 181–184.
Wood, Alexander. The Physics of Music. Chapman and Hall, 1975.
Wright, Paul and Paquette, Radnor. Highway Engineering. New York: John
Wiley and Sons, Inc., 1987.
</p>
</section> 
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->